<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A] true account of what was done by a Church of Christ in Exon (whereof Mr. Lewis Stucley is pastor) the eighth day of March, 1657. when two members thereof were excommunicated. Together with the judgement of the non-conformists in the dayes of Q. Elizabeth, and K. Iames, concerning excommunication by a particular church. [Pu]blished by an eye abd ear-witness.</title>
            <author>Mall, Thomas, b. 1629 or 30.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B26461</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829411</idno>
  <idno type="VID">207123</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248496516</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M335A</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829411</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99829411e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B26461)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207123)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1993:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A] true account of what was done by a Church of Christ in Exon (whereof Mr. Lewis Stucley is pastor) the eighth day of March, 1657. when two members thereof were excommunicated. Together with the judgement of the non-conformists in the dayes of Q. Elizabeth, and K. Iames, concerning excommunication by a particular church. [Pu]blished by an eye abd ear-witness.</title>
                  <author>Mall, Thomas, b. 1629 or 30.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 94 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by R.W. for Matthew Keinton, at the Fountain in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The Epistle" signed: Thomas Mall.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; C1 (pp. 23-24) lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Excommunication --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207123:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207123:1"/>
            <p>True Account Of What was done by a Church of Christ in <hi>Exon</hi> (whereof Mr. <hi>Lewis Stucley</hi> is Pastor) the eighth day of <hi>March,</hi> 1657. when two members thereof were Excommunicated.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ogether with the Judgement of the Non-conformists in the dayes of <hi>Q. Elizabeth,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <hi>K. Iames,</hi> concerning Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication by a particular Church.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>blished by an eye and ear-witness.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould thy lyes make men hold their peace? And when thou mockest, shall no man make thee ashamed? <bibl>
                  <hi>Job</hi> chap. <hi>11.</hi> ver. <hi>3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Nil dictum quod, non dictum prius.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inted by <hi>R. W.</hi> for <hi>Matthew Keinton,</hi> at the <hi>Fountain</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="excerpts_concerning_excommunication">
            <pb facs="tcp:207123:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207123:2"/>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ectè Excommunicati ab Ecclesia sunt in potestate Satanae ad interitum car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, <hi>1 Cor. 5.</hi> Si vero paenitentiam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt, &amp; recipiuntur, tum à Satana li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berantur. Histor. <hi>Nagdeb.</hi> cent. <hi>1. li. 2. p. 135, 47.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <p>EXcommunicationem indicari per modum illum loquendi, quo Apostolus usus est, <hi>1 Cor. 5 5.</hi> &amp; <hi>1 Tim. 1.20.</hi> Nempe tradere Satanae ad interitum carnis, rectè judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt multi ex veteribus, quia extra Ecclesiam Satanas regnat. <hi>Synop. Pur. Theol.</hi> conscript. <hi>P. Poliandrum, Rive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Walaeum, Thysium,</hi> Disp. <hi>48.40.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <p>WHAT is Excommunication? A giving up to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. <hi>Greenham. p.</hi> 843. of his works.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <p>ONE and the last of the Spiritual means of fear is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, whereby men are delivered to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. that delivering of the incestuous person can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a bare bodily punishment, but an excluding of a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from the Communion and fellowship of the Church &amp; must be done in the face of the Church by the consent
<pb facs="tcp:207123:3"/> of the whole Church, as appears <hi>ver.</hi> 2. &amp; 4. <hi>Perkins</hi> on <hi>Jude.</hi> p. 587.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <p>THE greater Excommunication (as distinct from suspension) putteth the Excommun cate from the Sacrament of the Lords body and blood, and depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth them of all that comfort; and strength of Grace which from it they might receive: it denieth to them the benefit of the Churches publique Prayers, and so leaveth them to themselves as forlorn and miserable wretches, and whence it is that they are said to be delivered, to Satan; because they are left (naked and void of all means to make resistance) unto his Will and Pleasure. <hi>Field</hi> of the Church. <hi>p.</hi> 23, 24.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <p>NEither is it anything else then Excommunication which the Apostle signifieth by delivering to Satan, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thorndick</hi> in his discourse of the right of the Church in a Christian state. <hi>page</hi> 34.</p>
               <p>The Censure of Excommunication cutteth men off from the Conversation of Christians, which forfeit the priviledges, to which they pretend, and so delivers them to Satan by consequence, as those that lodged without the camp of <hi>Israel,</hi> were in danger to be lick up by the <hi>Amalekite,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5 5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Thorndick</hi> in his Primitive Government of Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hes, <hi>page</hi> 91.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <p>THE end of excommunication is that he may be ashamed, that he may see himself alone, no compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but the Devil thought bad enough for him, and so be brought to sense and shame of his own vil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ness, which is the most necessary preparative to reformation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:207123:3"/> though a little before, binding, Excommunicating, delivering to Satan be made <hi>Synonima's.</hi> It followeth, Excommunication it is an Act of Mercy and Charity of all other the greatest, though under the shew of severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and wrath. Doctor <hi>Hammon</hi> of the power of the keyes, <hi>p.</hi> 117.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <p>IF the terror and horror of Excommunication (to be cast out of the Church, and delivered up into the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Satan) win not a sinner, nothing will. <hi>Caudry</hi> Church reform, promoted. <hi>p.</hi> 65.</p>
               <p>The last remedy is to shame him when he shall see himself abhorred and forsaken of all good men, and when all the People avoid his company as a leaprous person, accounting him not fit for humane society, being delivered to Satan. <hi>Idem. p.</hi> 68.</p>
               <p>Excommunication is a delivering a man over to the power of Satan. <hi>Idem. p.</hi> 85.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <p>
                  <hi>IOHN C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rnford</hi> (one of the six last that were burnt in <hi>England</hi> for the true Religion) when he heard himself, and his followers excommunicated, stirred with a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment zeal of God, and proceeding in a more true ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication against the Papists: in the name of them all pronounced sentence against them in these words. <hi>In the Name of our Lord Jesus Christ, and by the Power of his holy Spirit, and the Authority of his holy Catholick and Apostolick Church, we do give here into the hands of Satan to be destroyed the bodies of all those Blasphemers and Hereticks that do maintain any error against his most holy Word, or do condemn his most holy Truth for Heresie, to the maintaining of any false Church or feigned Religion:</hi> So that by this thy just judgement, most mighty God against thine Adversaries, thy true Religion may be known to
<pb facs="tcp:207123:4"/> thy Glory and our Comforts, and to the edifying of all our Nation; good Lord so be it. <hi>Trap</hi> on <hi>John</hi> 9.22.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <p>I Am their same opinion, who interpret the delivering to Satan of Excommunication, and so doth <hi>Gual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> himself; so doth the Syriack which readeth; that you (<hi>Corinthians</hi> may deliver such an one to Satan. If it was an act of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> then it was a Church-sensure not a Miracle. The Greek doth also carry it to be an Act of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> assembled together. We have also some, (though not all) of the Antients for us in this particular: as <hi>Balsamon</hi> in <hi>Canon.</hi> Epist <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>silij ad Amphilock. Can.</hi> 7. observeth. <hi>Gillespy's</hi> Aarons-rod blossoming. <hi>p.</hi> 435.</p>
               <p>Whether the Power of Excommunication <hi>in actu pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, seu quoad esse</hi> did belong to the collective body of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> or not, is a question controverted and to this day, <hi>sub judice lis est;</hi> yet even those who hold the affirmative part of the question, do notwithstanding say, that <hi>in actu secundo, seu quoad operari,</hi> the power pertained to their Bresbytery, which is confirmed by 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6 where the Apostle speaking of the censure of that incestuous man, saith not that it was inflicted by all, but by many, the Pastors and Elders of <hi>Corinth;</hi> how be it the execution and final act of that high censure was to be with the consent, and in the Presence of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. <hi>Gillespy's</hi> Asserion of the Government of the Church of <hi>Scotland. p.</hi> 115, 116.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <p>I Deny not but the faithfull convened; or were to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene in this meeting, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. with the eldership, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the meeting is demonstrated pastoral and presbyterial with spiritual Power from the special intended end in
<pb facs="tcp:207123:4"/> that act which was authoritatively to deliver the Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator to Satan. <hi>Rutherf.</hi> peacable. plea. <hi>p.</hi> 235.</p>
               <p>One and the same word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to purge out the leaven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. applyed both to Elders and Believers hath divers meanings according as it is applyed to divers subjects; so that the Elders did purge out and excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate one way, that is authoritatively, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did purge out the leaven another way, by a popular consenting that he should be excommunicate. <hi>Rutherfords</hi> peaceable plea for <hi>Pauls</hi> Presbytery in <hi>Scotland. p.</hi> 236.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <p>
                  <hi>APollonius</hi> saith, that the <hi>Walacrian</hi> Churches hold, that Classes and Synods have power to cast out from the Communion of the Churches, as a Heathen and a Publican, and to deliver to Satan an obstinate offending Church. <hi>p.</hi> 130. in English.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <head>Rules for Admission.</head>
               <p>THat such who desire to walk with God, and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in all ordinances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Be at a Church-meeting proposed to the Church for their approbation and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission. That they do then solemnly and seriously pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess their faith and Repentance before all the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That they do then seriously and solemnly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and promise, to walk with God and his People (particularly the Church to which they now joyn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves) according to the Rules of the Word of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.1.9. to the end: <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.38. and <hi>chap.</hi> 10. 1, 29. <hi>Josh.</hi> 24.21, 28. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. That if the Church do approve of their conversation, and profession, they be received; otherwise, desired to forbear, or excluded til the Church be satisfied; By the Church here is meant the whole body: or the Major number of the men at least, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="paragraph">
               <pb facs="tcp:207123:5"/>
               <head>Particular Rules for walking in Church-Order.</head>
               <p>THat all Admitted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yield and submit themselves to the Discipline of Christ in his Church, as it shall be made known to us from the Word: and may be to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification exercised in our particular Congregation, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 3, 4, 5, 6 <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That the consent of the whole Church, or at least the greater part of the men, be taken by the Pastor and Officers, in matters of weight and moment, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That such as shall privately offend, be first privately admonished; if that prevail not, then with two or three; if that prevail not, then let the matter be declared to the Church, and the offendor publickly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished by the Pastor: if that prevail not, let him be accounted as an <hi>Heathen, and a Publican,</hi> Mat. 18.15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That such as sin openly, be more speedily and severely dealt withal, and proceeded against, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.20, 24, 25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>per tot.</hi> Mr. <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ckel in his Church-Rules, pag.</hi> 4, 5, 7.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:207123:5"/>
            <head>To the Impartial Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Judge it needless for me to make any Apologie for my thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth in Print; if these Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers do not that for the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sher: 'Tis past the power of his Epistle, I shall no longer detain thee from their perusal, then to tell thee how they are connected. Ʋnderstand there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the <hi>8<seg rend="sup">th.</seg>
               </hi> of this instant <hi>March</hi> was appointed by a Church of Christ in this City, for the cutting off two offenders, that had been found guilty of several miscarriages; and of refusing private and publick admonition: In the beginning of the day, one of the Elders gave a brief Relation of the ends of their meeting: and then beg'd the presence of God with the Church in that days-work. Afterwards the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor Mr <hi>Lewis Stucley</hi> preached. The notes of which Sermon, I am glad I took in short-hand from his mouth, or otherwise thou mightest never have seen a true Copy of them. Sermon being ended, he prayed,
<pb facs="tcp:207123:6"/> and then proceeded to pronounce the sentence, which he closed with a second prayer. This great business being thus dispatched; some reasons were given for the Churches Re-entring into Covenant: and then a divine Blessing being implored; there was a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of all present, both Officers and Members.</p>
            <p>Thus hast thou a brief account of the most material passages of that day. Now because the main work thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> Excommunication by a particular Church furnished with Officers, is become so great a wonder; I have annexed some Sheets gathered out of some Rare Pieces of men Famous in their, and this Generation, relating to that affair. If my transcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions either of the Sermon, or of the eminent old Non-conformists Assertions and Reasons be imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; I hope thou wilt over-look all the Errat<hi>'s</hi> seeing I had very few dayes (not weeks) for the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting, and writing the whole for the Press. If tho<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> beest resolved to try all things, and hold fast tha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> which is good: and not to entertain or reject an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> thing for its seeming Novelty: I doubt not, but afte<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> thou hast perused this Discourse: thou wilt accoun<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> me</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine, and th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Truths friend<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Thomas Mall<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Exon.
<date>March. <hi>22. 1657, 8.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:207123:6"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 5.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>To deliver such a one unto Satan for the Destruction of the flesh, that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the former part of this Chapter we have these two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Apostles reprehension of the neglect of Church-Discipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And secondly, The Apostles care to supply the neglect thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, The Apostles Reprehension of the neglect of Church-Discipline; where we have 1. A Church Delinquent, but one in the Chapter, or but one no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious; an <hi>incestuous person,</hi> that is, but one to such a height as was fitted, and prepared for the throwing out: and under this head we have 1. the nature of his sin described; and that two wayes: 1. It was <hi>incest;</hi> and then 2. such as the Heathens would not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, they detested it <hi>verse</hi> 1. <hi>It is reported commonly that there is fornication among you, and such fornication, as is not so much as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med among the Gentiles,</hi> &amp;c. And as we have the nature of the sin; So secondly we have the notorietie, the publikeness of it. <hi>It is commonly reported,</hi> generally known <hi>verse</hi> 1. But then, as we have a Church-Delinquent fitted for Excommunication: So 2. Here we have the Churches sin; and the Church is charged for three things. 1. That they rested in a good opinion of their own condition, while they were not chargeable with such an abomination: they prided themselves likely, and likely were puffed up, that they were not so unclean, as that man <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>And ye are puffed up,</hi> &amp;c. 3. He accuseth them for not publikely sorrowing for this scandalous sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>and have not rather mourned,</hi> &amp;c. That which the Apostle expected from them was, that they should have demeaned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in such a manner, as that they should have evidenced to others, that they were sensible that God was dishonoured, and that they abominated such a sin.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:207123:7"/>
            <p>But then thirdly, he chargeth them for their neglecting to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate this man <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>And have no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rather mourned, that he that hat<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> done this deed, might be taken away from among you.</hi> He would have had them so to have sorrowed, as that their sorro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> should have ended in Excommunication. But it is not the work of the Apostle to charge home sin only; But</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Apostles care is also to supply their neglect: and here we have 1. the Apostle encouraging of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Church to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to a sentence <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>For I verily as absent in body, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> present in spirit, have judged a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ready,</hi> &amp;c. as if he had said, I am free to do what I put you upon doing; and 2. as if he did not much doubt that they would submit: he sheweth the manner ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the sentence must be executed <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>In the Name of our Lord Jesus Christ, when ye are gathered together,</hi> &amp;c. 3. He she eth them who is the effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cause of Excommunication; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd here is a principal cause; <hi>the Power of the Lord Jes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> Christ co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>curring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith his Church <hi>ver.</hi> 4. with <hi>the power of our Lord Jesus Christ;</hi> and the Ministerial cause, the Church <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>when ye are ga hered together.</hi> 4. That things may be well managed, he setteth down the form of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: to deliver the Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch-Delinquent to <hi>Satan, ver.</hi> 5. <hi>To deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver such a one to Satan.</hi> 5. He giveth them the end of this Church-Discipline; and that is double. 1. <hi>The destruction of the flesh.</hi> 2. <hi>that the soul may be saved</hi> ver. 5. <hi>to deliver such a one to Satan, for the destruction of the flesh, that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give me leave a little, as it were in a paraphrase, to run over the words to my Text. As if the Apostle had said, It is a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat shame, and reproach that lieth upon you, that sins of unnatural uncleanness are found among you. And that such offences are committed among you, as civil nations, though not Christians would a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hor to be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of; namely, <hi>a son to use his fathers wife;</hi> and you are so far from being humbled at this, that you are secure, and <hi>puffed up</hi> with your Priviledges, that you do not mind the dishonour of God here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by: you do not consider that this is a crime fit for censure; Now the Apostle supposing their consciences are convinced of this sin, and enquiring what is to be done? He tels them <hi>ver.</hi> 3. that his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, that he should be excommunicated: and least they should say, we will not do it without thee in thy absence; to temove that, he tells them, that though he be absent from them, yet that should not hinder: for though I be absent, I am of this Judgement <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>For I verily as absent in body, but present in spirit have judged al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, as though I were present, concerning him that hath so done this deed.</hi> But we know not how to proceed against him,<note place="margin">Let the Church be convened.</note> we are convinced he ought to be removed, But how shall it be done? Why, saith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:207123:7"/> get a Church meeting; and the <hi>power of the Lord Jesus</hi> will be with them so met, and what then? Why, Excommunicate him. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> shall that be done? <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liver him over to Satan.</hi> I, but this is a very unlikely means to reduce him; Is Satan to help the Church? or will Satan be useful to save the sinner? Yea, saith the Apostle: though Satan intentionally will not reduce a sinner, yet God will over-rule him; God will use him, and employ him in the work; therefore <hi>Deliver such a one to Satan for the destruction of the flesh, that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The obse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vation I shall give you is this:
<q>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> That it is the will of God, that a Church of Christ should excommunicate their scandalous members, when they remain incorrigible.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here we are to consider these things. First, Who those are that are to Excommunicate. Secondly, Wherein Excommunication ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Thirdly, Why the Church must Excommunicate. Fourthly, What a fearful Sentence this is. Fifthly, Answer some Objections, and give the matter of Fact, and so some uses.</p>
            <p>First, Who are to Excommunicate? the fourth <hi>verse</hi> tells you, when ye are gathered together, the Church convened: the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Excommunication perteineth to the whole Church: So Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> on this Scripture. The Apostle would not take the whole pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to himself, saith <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> he would not Excommunicate him alone; the <hi>Pope</hi> and the Bishops have been bold this way: but so would not the Apostle. But when ye are gathered together. It is a dangerous course that so great a Sentence, as is Excommunication (saith <hi>Peter Martyr</hi>) should be in the hand of one particular person: If the power were in the Apostle alone, the Apostle were more blame-worthy then the Church, for suffering this unclean member in this Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch; but the Apostle blameth the Church, that they did not <hi>cast him out;</hi> they should have taken him away from among them <hi>ver.</hi> 3. And he prescribeth the manner of excommunication to them, that they mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t proceed upon him; and after he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>resseth them to put the sentence in execution: that they should <hi>purge away the old leaven ver</hi> 7. And again <hi>ver.</hi> 13. that they should <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t away f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om among themselves tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wicked person:</hi> The Arguments to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force th s Exhor ation concern the whole Church: From the danger of infection; that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s one; such a sin being as <hi>leaven,</hi> that will diffuse from the whole <hi>lump;</hi> the whole are in danger <hi>ver.</hi> 6.7. <hi>your glorying is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good: know ye not that a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump? Purge out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herefore the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d leaven, that ye may be a new lump, as ye are unleavened:</hi> Again, the whole were to keep the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ristian-pass-over, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did theirs; where the Leaven was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:207123:8"/> to be cast out of every house, and every one was to contribut<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> what he could to the casting it out. Besides the Apostle had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a former Epistle to this Church, wherein he had advised th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> whole Church not to keep <hi>company with Fornicators,</hi> verse 9. suc<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> he means as they had power over; for some there were that wer<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> without, and these he leaveth to Gods judgement, <hi>verse</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Papists (and so others) object, that though the Apostl<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> commanded that the Act should be done in the face of the Church, ye<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> (say they) the Judgement and Authority of giving sentence, was i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> himself, and not in the whole multitude, as the Protestants affirm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> It seems then the Protestants hold so, that it lieth in the Church, if the Authors of the <hi>Rhemish</hi> Testament wrong them not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Papists also (it seems) grant that the Act should be done in the face of the whole Church: and if excommunication of mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers; then admission of Members should be in the face of th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> whole Church. There is the same reason for the admission o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Members into the Church, as for the casting of them out. I wis<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> this were considered by them who admit, and suspend Members i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> corners and Chambers, without the privitie of them that shoul<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> be present at such a work.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But for a full answer to this, let Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> give it i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> his notes on the <hi>Rhemish</hi> Testament. First, It is clear (saith he) that though the Apostle judged him worthy of excommunication yet if the Ministrs of the Church, with the rest of the Body, ha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> not shut him out, he had not been taken for a Publican. Secondly It is clear the Apostle would not have them do it, but when gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together: he would not have them to excommunicate him, but a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> a Church-meeting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Papists object further, that the Church are but witnesse and lookers on of the Action.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> giveth many Answers to this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. First, (saith he) if the Church were only assembled to bea<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> witness; then <hi>Pauls</hi> Spirit was only to bear witness: for the perso<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal presence of the Church, and the Apostles spiritual presenc<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> were met together in this affair. Besides.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He saith, <hi>Do not ye judge them that are within;</hi> surely that i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> much more then to be Witnesses, and Lookers on; for the Apostl<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> useth the same work to declare the Churches Power, as he doth t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> declare his own Power; and how unlikly is it that the same word i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the same chapter, about the same matter, should signifie to judg<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> when applyed to <hi>Paul,</hi> and to be but a Witness, when applyed to th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Church?</p>
            <p>And that we are not alone in this; to this also agreeth Dr. <hi>Fu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> on the <hi>Rhemish</hi> Testament. The Authority of excommunicatio<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:207123:8"/> (saith he) pertaintaineth to the whole Church, and the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours execute that Authority in the name of Christ, and in the name of the Church to avoid confusion. Thus saith <hi>Paraeus</hi> on the place, the Church are not witnessess only: but judges of this Action, and he concurs with <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> of whom before.</p>
            <p>So Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> (that great champion for Presbytery) the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle (saith he) sheweth what was their duty as Christians con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened together in a Church-way: the Apostle doth not command one christian, but the Church <hi>gathered together in the name of the Lord Jesus to cast himout;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> we apply it (saith he) to the casting of scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous persons out of the Church, as leaven was to be put out of the Houses of all who were to eat the Passover. But.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Wherein lieth Excommunication? It lieth in the Churches, delivering up a scandalous impenitent sinner to <hi>Satan:</hi> It lieth in turning such a one out of the house of God; and from the company of the Lords people, and putting him into the Kingdom and power of the Devil. To make his sentence full, three thing are requisite (though not all alike necessary.) 1. It should pass <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rom a good intention and heart; and not from a revengeful princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. 2. It should be when the cause is just and clear, and clearly proved.</p>
            <p>And 3. Executed according to Christs order, that is, after pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Admonition, unless the sin be publique as the incestuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons was; when we have gone privately, and then more publiquely, (if the offence be private) and the party remain incorrigible, then the sentence is to be pronounced in a Church-assemblie convened for that end, in the name of Christ, and then it is of validity, yea of such validity, that Christ hath said expresly, <hi>whatsoever ye shall bind on earth shall be bound in heaven,</hi> Mat. 18.18.</p>
            <p>It is a committing the incorrigible delinquent unto Satan, not an absolute giving of him up, but a committing to him, as of a priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to a Jailor. <hi>Non dedendum sed committendum</hi> saith <hi>Asanasius</hi> on the place.</p>
            <p>First he is not delivered to Satan morally, this is a sinfull deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance to give over one to Satan that he may work in him as in his work-house, and as in a child of disobedience. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. for we suppose that a soul already converted, may be excommunicated, but he cannot be thus <hi>delivered unto Satan,</hi> so as to be under that power that natural men are. But.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he is delivered unto Satan penally, to a penal Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turer, and who is to work sororw and fear in the conscience for sin, and to scare the Offender, and that way to humble him, <hi>that so the Spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This form of Excommunication. as <hi>Deodati</hi> and <hi>Paraeus</hi> think, is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:207123:9"/> taken from <hi>Saul,</hi> (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16, 14.) when rejected of the Lord. Fo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Excommunication is a partial rejection from God, and whilst th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> party is excommunicated, those influences from God that wer<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> wont to be given, are suspended from him, though a gracious soul. I<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the primitive times it was followed with horrors of Spirit, and tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments of body. And <hi>Josephus</hi> reports that those that were foun<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in any considerable sin, and cast out of the congregation, came t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> some miserable death. To be short, I suppose that the essence o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> excommunication lieth in severing sinners from Saints Communion and so throwing them back into Satans Kingdom. Delivering to Satan, includeth two things. 1. Here is <hi>terminus a quo,</hi> from whence delivered from the Church: from the Society of the Faithfull they are taken off from them, and then 2. <hi>terminus ad quem,</hi> unto whom, and that is said to be the divel. The word <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver</hi> in signification it is a relative word, it seemeth to have a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to asking or demanding. The Devil he is called the <hi>Accuser of the Brethren,</hi> Rev. 12.10. and he is called an <hi>Adversary,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.8. or an Impleader; When he hath an Accusation against a Church or Member:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> he demands to have the sinner delivered over to him, that he may torment him, and the Lord is pleased to answer this request of his, and bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Church deliver up the Offendor to Satan; and he is so delivered up, when he is thrust out from before the Lord, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from the Saints communion; he is no longer to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (saith <hi>Barcus) membrum Christi &amp; ecclesiae, sed Satanae</hi>) a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Christ and the Church, but a member of Satan of Satans Kingdom. But then.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Why must the Church excommunicate, or why must they deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to Satan? Before I shall answer this, for method-sake I shall premise that look, as hell consist <hi>in paena damni &amp; paena sensus,</hi> so doth this punishment in the pain of loss, and the pain of sense: here somewhat that the sinner is deprived of, and somewhat that he is sensibly under, as a misery and torment; somewhat he is cut off from, and deprived of, and some positive evil that he lieth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: he is deprived of the society of Gods people, and actually set under the tormenting power of the devil; we need not puzel our selves much, what course Satan takes with the Offendor so deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered: sure it is such a Power that he hath over him, as Christ hath appointed for the <hi>destruction of the flesh, that the soul may be saved.</hi> Accordingly I shall put this into two questions.</p>
            <p>Quest. 1. <hi>Why are scandalous m mbers to be cut off from the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Quest. 2. <hi>Why are they to be deliv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red to Satan?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Quest. 1. <hi>Why are they to be cut off from the hous<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. Because that God hath forsaken them, and therefore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:207123:9"/> so should the Church: God is departed from them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church should leave them: the ground of our Union with them (whom we are to procede on) was their visible closing with Christ: now when that visibility ceaseth, when that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance of religion ceaseth, the Union is to be dissolved. It was founded and built upon visible holiness, and when visible ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness ceaseth, the Union must cease: he that opposeth God and Christ in his Laws, is to be opposed by all that are Christs: there ought to be the same mind in all that are the servants of Christ, that was in Christ their Master; they are to esteem whom Christ esteemeth, and to hate whom he hateth; when these persons outwardly closed with Christ, they outwardly sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed, that they would be the Lords; and therefore we owned them: now they have cast away these cords from them, they have broken Covenant, neglected the house of God, contemned admonition private and publique, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Therefore are they are be cast out from Communion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause indeed there can be no Communion with them. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acted by indifferent Laws, they cannot be owned: we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not walk with them: they that are sound, they own Christ as their Law-giver and Head: these reject him as their Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver and Head; we cannot agree with such: Sanctity and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suality cannot agree; the Motions and Original of the godly and wicked are contrary: the Saints Original is from Heaven, and the wicked mans from earth, and their motion are contrary, the one downward, the other upward, like two ballances, if one goeth up, the other goeth downward, therefore they must needs be put on contrary practises: for that which is <hi>born of the flesh</hi> will oppose that which is born of the <hi>Spirit;</hi> and though <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Esau</hi> may for a while be in the womb of the Church, yet there will be strugling till they part, they cannot admit of no accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation: What <hi>Communion hath Light with Darkness? What Concord hath God with Belial? What part have Believers with Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels? What agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols.</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle bids us in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14, 15.16. <hi>Be ye not unequally yoaked together with Ʋnbelievers, for what fellowship hath Righteousness with Ʋnrighteousness?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Depart from me all ye Workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity;</hi> saith <hi>David, Psal.</hi> 6.8. It is an intollerable Wo to good men to be forced to be amonst wicked men. <hi>Psal.</hi> 120.5. <hi>Wo is me that I sojorn in</hi> Mesech, <hi>that I dwell in the Tents of</hi> Kedar. But then.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God hath promised his peculiar residence among his Church, but he hath not promised it, save upon these terms, that he may be in a clean house, and not among beasts, now all contumaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous persons are as beasts, God will not dwell with them, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:207123:10"/> them to Spiders and Cockatrices, <hi>Isa,</hi> 59.5. to <hi>Vipers,</hi> Mat<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 12.34. <hi>to Scorpions. Ezek.</hi> 2.6. these are no fit company fo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> God or Man, therefore to be cast out: look into the Scriptur<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> again, and you shall see that wicked men are called <hi>Lions,</hi> and they are savage, <hi>Psal.</hi> 22.21. they are called <hi>Bears, Isa.</hi> 11.7. an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> they are cruel, they are called <hi>Dragons, Ezek.</hi> 29.3. and they ar<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> hidious, <hi>Dogs, Mat.</hi> 7.6. and they are bloody, they are called <hi>Wolve<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Ezek,</hi> 22.27. and they are ravenous.</p>
            <p>And what, Do you think God will dwell with Wolves, Bears<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Dogs, surely no? And therefore the Church seeing that this i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the way to keep God among them, by removing Dogs <hi>(with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out are Dogs)</hi> therefore they are met together this day to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>move such, in whose presence God cannot delight, nor sobe<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Saints.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There is danger of infection to the Church, if this leaven<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> continued; and therefore they are to be thrown out. <hi>A litt<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> leaven l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aveneth the whole lump:</hi> it is the Argument of the A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>postle in this chapter to press them to excommunication, <hi>verse</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 7. <hi>Your glorying is not good</hi> (saith the Apostle) <hi>Know ye not, th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> a little leaven leaveneth the whole Lump? Purge out therefore the o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> leaven that ye may be a new lump, as ye are unleavened; &amp;c.</hi> Our E<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glish Proverb is significant, one scabbed sheep infects a who<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> flock: a man cannot take this fier into his bosoms, and not be bu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.28. <hi>Can one go upon hot coals, and his feet not be burnt<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> neither can a man handle this pitch without defilement, <hi>Psal.</hi> 10 35. <hi>They were mingled among the heathens, and learned their work</hi> And therefore Mr <hi>Rutherford</hi> in his due right of of Presbyteri<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>page</hi> 76. observeth, that the power of excommunication was give<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> by Christ to a Church upon this formal ground and reason, b<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cause a Congregation is a number of sinfull men, who may<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> scandalized, and who may be infected with the company of<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> scandalous person, for if a Congregation were a company of A<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gels, which cannot be infected; such Power should not be giv<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> them, so that as Nature hath given hands to a man to defend hi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>self from injuries and violence: and horns to oxen to hold off v<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>olence; so Christ hath given to his Church the Power of exco<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munication, as spiritual Armour to ward off and defend the co<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tagion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icked fellowship. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.9, 10. <hi>A little leaven le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>veneth the whole lump. I have confidence in you through the Lo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that ye will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> none otherwise minded: but he that troubleth you, sh<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar his Judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment whoever he be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the members may be corrupted by one rotten one, as<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> rotten coar may corrupt a hoard; a Gangreen thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Toe, will soon endanger the vital parts, if it be not cut off fro<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the body natural, and it holdeth in the Church, where t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:207123:10"/> several members are in danger from one corrupted part; so that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we use the remedy appointed by God to eschew the contagion of the wicked, we are in danger: and therefore, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.24, 25. <hi>Make no frienship with an angry man, and with a furious man thou shalt not go, least thou learn his way, and get a snare to thy soul.</hi> And again, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.8, 9. <hi>Remove thy way far from her, and come not nigh <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>he door of her house, least thou give thine honour unto others, and thy <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ears unto the cruel.</hi> It is dangerous to come near the house of such, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.4. <hi>And I heard another Voice from Heaven, saying, Come <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ut of her my people, that ye be not partakers of her sins, and that ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eive not of her plagues.</hi> And though we should not be actually cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>upted, yet we shall sin, and tempt the Lord, in keeping our selves <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nder such a temptation, when we have power to deliver our selves <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rom it, by cutting off them, that will eat as a Gangreen, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>.17. <hi>Their word will eat as doth a canker: of whom is</hi> Hymenus, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd</hi> Philaetus. The whole lump is in danger, that is the Argument <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>f our Apostle here. All the Church, they that are most confident, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nd pride themselves most are in danger: therefore the leaven is to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e cast out, that is, not the sin abstractly considered, but <hi>he that <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ath done the deed.</hi> The Antients have been curious this way; and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>erefore <hi>Sozomene</hi> reports concerning the Emperour <hi>Theodosius</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>or, that he being willing to confer with <hi>Eunomius,</hi> the <hi>Arian</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>op, his wife <hi>Placilla</hi> the Empress earnestly diswaded him, least <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e being perverted by his speeches, should begin to like of his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>sie. Nothing is more difficult then to be familiar with sinners, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nd not to be infected by them: by being encouraged, or seduced, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nd even constrained to sin by the conversations of rotten fellow-<gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>embers. If <hi>Corah</hi> be of a troublesome spirit, and be over-run with <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ride and envy, he quickly draweth in two hundred and fifty into <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e conspiracy; men <hi>famous in the Congregation and men of renown.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>is abode was so near the <hi>Reubenites,</hi> that he soon infuseth his poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n into <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abyran,</hi> and had not all <hi>Israel</hi> withdrawn spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ly, they had been in danger of infection with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itness.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If Excommunication should not be with reference to scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>us members, Christ and his Chruch would suffer by connivance, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d sparing this Rod: it is a kind of justifying a sinner, when we <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> not punish his sin, according to the power of the Lord Jesus gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n us for this end. Religion becometh ridiculous, and Profession is <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ught to scorn, when sinners are let alone; and therefore we ought <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r Christs honour to pull off the Masking Robes; and the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rds wherewith these have deceived us, and others to, and to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ew to the world, that we do not Judge them.</p>
            <p>But upon this account, because they rise u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> against the Lawes of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hrist; we are to declare plainly that they are guilty of such sins <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> make them not worthy of a Name in the House of God. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207123:11"/> may aim at this in the first <hi>ver. It is certainly heard that th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> is fornication amongst you;</hi> this bad report he makes the first groun<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of proceeding to Excommunication,, as if he had said, It is a di<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>honour to Christ that there are such things commonly talked o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> therefore timely declare against them. So say I, it is Reported th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> there is among you a notorious lyar, and a lawless woman, th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> knoweth no subjection at home and or abroad, to her own husban<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> or to the Church of God; It will argue little affection to Christ:<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you let these alone, if you let Rebels against his Majesty alone<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> therefore purge out these, bear witness against these, that t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> wicked may not say, we have lyars and disobedient persons among us uncontrouled: <hi>ut sitis nova massa,</hi> that you may appear to<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> such a lump, such a Cong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>egation as is unleavened.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Therefore are we to throw out such to deter others from s<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> that these may be examples to others; when the Magistrate gro<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth careless, sin groweth bold, when he doth not punish sin, sinn<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> grow bold-faced; not only the offenders themselves, but others<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> so sin after their similitude in hope of the same impunity, 1 <hi>T<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 5.20. <hi>Them that sin rebuke openly that the rest also may fear;</hi> Here<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the End of God, and this is a blessed end that others may fear.</p>
            <p>By the way give me leave to reflect on our selves: this is a d<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of taking shame to our selves; what do we know but that, if<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> had discharged our duty sooner on the lyar, we might have preve<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed the others fail, her disobedience and pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>versness of spirit? T<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Lord lay not this to our charge: if publick and notorious offend<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> had been made publick examples, others might have feared; this<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the End that God aimeth at in punishing, that all <hi>Israel</hi> sho<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> hear and fear, and do no more such wickedness, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.11. If<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> partake of their sin, we must expect to partake of their judgeme<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. And lastly, Because God delights that the punishment of a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be like the sin in kind: the punishment commonly bears the Im<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and superscription of the sin; so true is it, <hi>that what a man sow<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that shall he reap,</hi> Gal. 6.7. God often returns the sins of Chu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> members so on them, that they may read the name of their<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> stampt upon their punishment; <hi>Eye for eye,</hi> that was of old, <hi>E<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 21.24. These have turned their backs on pure Ordinances, theref<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> they shall no longer enjoy them: they were careless and rega<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>less of Church-orders; and now by the orders of the House<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> God, they are to be turned out from behold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng our faith, and<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, that they may say, as that wretched <hi>Adonibezel,</hi> Judg. 17. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> have done so God hath requited me;</hi> That is a dreadful word, <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 7.13. <hi>therefore it is come to pass, that as he called, and they would h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar; so they cryed, and I would not hear, saith the Lord of H<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> God hath cryed by Officers, by Members, but these wretches wo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot hear the Church; well saith God, will not they hear me<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:207123:11"/> shall come to pass they shall cry, and I will not hear; Christ giveth Orders to throw them to day out of his special care, and the Churches daily inspection.</p>
            <p>Qestion 2. <hi>Why are hey to be delivered to S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tan?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answer,</hi> It may be a sufficient Reason that it is the will of God it should be so. But I shall name two other Reasons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there may be some proportion betwixt their punishment and their visible state and condition. They appear to be children of Hell, and therefore fitter for fellowship with damned spirits, then to be associates of the Lord and his peo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le. <hi>Ye are of your Father the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vil, and the lusts of your father ye will do,</hi> Joh. 8.44. If they will do the works of the Devil, the Devils company is fitter for them then the fellowship of the people of God.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But perhaps the parties have faith: and what will ye deliver such to Satan?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I answer, they do not appear to us as Believers: they that live in the neglect of any known duty wilfully, are not to be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on as Believers; they have no more visible faith to me then an Heathen. My Brethren, <hi>de occultis non judicat Ecclesi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> we do not look to secret things: He that liveth in any known sin, and refuseth to repent of it, is visibly unregenerate. And that is our quarrel, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Lords quarrel with them, this day ours, because the Lords. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the church hath proceeded on a person, he is to be looked on with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Grace, because none appeareth but the contrary. It is said of <hi>Cain</hi> that he was of <hi>that wicked one,</hi> 1 John 3.12. And all that live in sin, &amp; blush not to be seen in the practice of it, they look like the Devil.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the flesh may be destroyed, and the spirit may be saved in the day of Christ.</hi> But more of this by and by under the fifth general.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I shall shew you what a fearful sentence this is. And here I shall distinguish as before.</p>
            <p>First, It is a fearful sentence to be cast out of a Church. A very se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere sentence; and this will appear if we consider a few things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Gods people in Church-Relation, they stand nearly Related unto God, in the Relation of children to a father, that is a near Relation; they are children, and God is their Father; they are sons and daughters, and he their Father; In the Relation of a wife to an Husband, the Lambs wife, so the Church is called; in as near a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation as members to the head; <hi>they are members of Christs body, bone of his bone, flesh of his flesh:</hi> what a fearful judgement is it to be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from these? to be pulled as it were from the body of Christ, from the flesh of Christ? to be cut off from the bones of Christ! they are called the Excellent of the Earth, <hi>Isa.</hi> 43.4. <hi>Since thou wast precious in my sight, thou hast been honourable, and I have loved thee: therefore will I give men for thee, and people for thy life.</hi> It is a credit to a man to keep company with honourable persons:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:207123:12"/> but to be burned out of their Societie is a sore, and bitter thing. For a Noble man to be degraded, and live amongst scullions; this is nothing to the being thrown out of the Assembly of Gods people among the pots of the earth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There are choice blessings entailed on a Church estate, which they are cut off from. God hath said <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.17. <hi>The Lord thy God in the midst of thee is mighty, he will save, he will rejoyce over thee with joy: he will rest in his love, he will joy over thee with singing: Here is a promise</hi> to <hi>Zion;</hi> the Lord thy God will rest in them. God will not rest with Excommunicates, <hi>Psalm</hi> 87.2. <hi>The Lord loveth the gates of</hi> Zion, <hi>more then all the dwellings of</hi> Jacob. God delights in the publick communion of his people, more then in all their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate dwellings; these are to be turned out from that Society which God loveth. Again <hi>Isa.</hi> 46.13. <hi>And I will place Salvation in</hi> Zion <hi>for</hi> Israel <hi>my Glory.</hi> These are to be turned out from salvation to day, from the place of salvation. The Name of the Church is <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah Shammah, Ezek.</hi> 48.35. <hi>The Lord is there:</hi> To be turned out of the place where the Lord is, how sad is it? <hi>Psal.</hi> 76.2. <hi>In</hi> Salem <hi>is his Tabernacle, and his dwelling place in Zion;</hi> What a sad thing is it to be turned out of the house where God is resident? <hi>Psal.</hi> 27.4. <hi>One thing have I desired of the Lord, that will I seek after, that I may dwell in the house of the Lord all the daies of my life, to behold the beauty of the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, and to enquire in his Temple.</hi> There God unvail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himself; these are to be denied this one thing that <hi>David</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired: there are choice manifestations of God there, and these may not hope to enjoy them whilst in an Excommunicate estate. Again in <hi>Isa.</hi> 25.6. God promiseth that in <hi>this Mountain he will make a feast of fat things, a feast of wines on the lees: of fat things full of marrow, of wines on the lees well refined.</hi> These are to be turned out from this feast of fat things, <hi>Psalm</hi> 36.7, 8. <hi>How excellent is thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindness, O God! therefore the children of men put their trust un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the shadow of thy wings. They shall be abundantly satisfied with the fatness of thy House, and thou shalt make them drink of the River of thy Pleasures.</hi> Nay, <hi>David</hi> found that all his springs were in the Church, <hi>Psal.</hi> 87.7. All his joys, and inlargements he got them in the Church. How sad is it to have these springs so dammed up, that that we cannot enjoy them? Nay, to the Church is committed the Covenants, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. and the Seals of the Covenant too; you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not singly have the Seals of the Covenant; but as joyned with the people of God? What a sad thing is it to be put in such a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where one shall not enjoy the benefit of the Covenant.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Gods people inchurched have the Image of God shining upon them: they have or should have choice Graces, which are indeed very delightfull. <hi>Seneca</hi> could say, that the very look of a good man did please him. If the look of a good man did please an heathen,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:207123:12"/> should it not please much more a Christian? and if the look of one good man, What should the look of many? if one star be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, what is a constellation? It must needs be a sweet thing to be in a Communion with the Lords people, to be in the midst of these beds of spices, <hi>Can.</hi> 6.2. <hi>My beloved is gone down into his garden, into the beds of Spices to feed in the gardens and to gather lillies</hi> It is as sad to be thrust out of their company from the sight of the graces of the Lords people: the appearance of these Graces, are lost to Excommunicates. Saints in Communion have a mighty advantage by seeing the Conversation of Church-members, to see how they deny themselves, how they trample the world under their feet, to see a company of Believers part from life rather t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en from a little Command; this is taken to see their feet stand in an even place, not walking halting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and uncomly, but keeping Judgement and doing Righteousness at all times, <hi>Psal.</hi> 106.3. to see their hands filled with both the Tables, having an equal respect to all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, these are glorious sights, but such as excommunicates may not enjoy; for they are to be put away from the midst of them. Examples of imitation or caution are very cogent and taking: they work more on us sometimgs then Doctrines: we are more prone to be affected with what we see, then what we here. Those that will not be wrought on by Sermons, may by conversations. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Likewise ye wives be in subjection to your own husbands, that if any obey not the word, they also may without the word be won by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation of the wives.</hi> Now what a sad thing is it to be turned out from beholding the Conversations of the Lords people! this is a dreadful sentence, a little piece or Hell,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Saints in Communion are engaged to be faithfull to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers souls, in watching over one another, and in reproving one another. But all this is to be lost to day. These are to lose all this.</p>
            <p>Likely they did not much care for it, the more is the pitty. But Mannah is Mannah, though such proud and filthy stomacks nauseate it. God will loose us to day from that particular tie that we were before under to these wretches. My Brethren, have not you found advantages by watching over one anothers quickning one another, councilling one another, and stirring up the Graces of one another? And when you have come off from one another; Have you not been more inflamed with love to God, more humbled in your own eyes, more prepared for sufferings, more dis-engaged from the world? Think then what a loss this is to be deprived of these helps.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To be delivered to Satan, is also a further proof of the sharpness of this Rod, and the weight and heaviness of it Though it be hard to tell which is worse: as I tould you but now.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:207123:13"/> The delivery supposeth a Demand, the Devil cometh, and d<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandeth of God such a Member (she is mine saith the Devil,<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> have <hi>been a Lier from the Beginning,</hi> and such a one is she, she hat<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> learned to lie after me, and therefore give her up. What saith Go<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to us, deliver up such a Lier to Satan? take her devil and torme<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> her, and vex her, put forth some Power on her for the destruct<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the flesh: Satan cometh on again; There is another i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> this fold that I demand saith he: <hi>I</hi> demand her that hath remove<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the bounds in her family in imitation of me: when I was in thy fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mily, I was not contented with my then station: I was not hig<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> enough: I would pirck up, and be above: and so hath she<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> she hath sinned after my likeness, give me that lawless woman give me all my Children.</p>
            <p>O saith God! That you did it: O my Church when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened! Deliver her also to Satan. I have given him leav<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to molest and disquiet her: do not with-hold her, but deliver her O Beloved! Is not this a fearfull Judgement? therefore it is called a curse: It is an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Is it not sad for God t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> curse such a one, and to say, the devil take such an one? remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for the Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be commanded in the name of Christ to curse such an one, to bid the Devil take such a woman, such a liar, such a contumacious woman; here <hi>vox populi est vox Dei:</hi> to go forth from the Church of Christ with the curse of God and man, how terrible is it? It is like the final sentence, <hi>depart from me, &amp;c.</hi> If we must depart, let us go into some good place and good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, no, but into the Devils company: but let us be at liberty, no, but chains must be put on: <hi>ye must be bound, Mat.</hi> 18.18. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> terrible is this? Beloved know this of a truth, whom ye this day shall bind on earth, shall bo bound in Heaven: and those poor souls that shall be under the curse of God to day, shall never be delivered from it without Repentance from these sins of theirs. Look as <hi>Godliness h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th the promises of this life, and that which is to come;</hi> so Ungodliness hath the curse of this life, and that which is to come. They are cursed, if they repent not to the day of Christ. <hi>Quis non exhorreat se trad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Satanae summo host<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Dei.</hi> Who would not tremble saith <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> to be delivered to Satan, the greatest enemy that God hath in the world: to be under the power of a cruel Tyrant, to be a Galli-slave to the Turk, were a great mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy; but alas no Magistrate, no Power so cruel and malicious, as Satan is: to lie under such a cruel enemy that hates, the soul, and persons so exceedingly. It cannot but be a very great Affliction.</p>
            <p>I sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ak this that I might bespeak you, and my o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n soul to pitty these poor forlo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n souls. That in putting them under the Power of the Devil, ye may she<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> campassion. You that are servants, do not ye account it a sad thing to be under wicked Masters? <hi>David</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:207123:13"/> reckoneth it amongst other great curses, <hi>set thou a wicked man over <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> that is a curse, <hi>Psal.</hi> 109.6. O what is it then to set a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Devil over a soul? What is it to have a wicked Spirit <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>er one? Nay the <hi>wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ked one</hi> as he is called, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.12? <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ear my Brethren, that the work we are about to day, though it <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> such sad work, doth not lie near enough to our hearts; nay as <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d as it is, I fear it maketh some besotted sinners to laugh this <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y: but surely did these consider the fearful nature of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, it might turn their laughter into weeping. Whatever <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>untenance Excommunicates may have amongst us, yet an excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unicate person was so odious to the Jews; that besides that they <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d shut him out of the Synagouge; if they did but meet such an <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e, they looked on it as a special mis-fortune, as a special token <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> some sad tidings, which would befall them. So much was this censure of the Church reverenced in those days, that it was accounted worse then five deaths.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Iews.</note> Will you hear Mr. <hi>Greenham's</hi> Opinion of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tes; they are among <hi>Ziims</hi> and <hi>Jiims,</hi> among the Owls and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ragons; they are as in Hell, and from the Congregation of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rist. To say no more of this: if God saith, take him Jailor, if the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>evil he the Keeper, and a Saint, or another be the Prisoner, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>u may guess how he shall be used: O! how will hetear and rend <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> conscience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But will you say why so fearfull a sentence? <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>What is the end of Excommunication?</hi> that is the fifth thing.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, What doth God intend in all this? I answer, that this <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ting out it is a medicinal punishment; it is Physick, and it is <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> last Physick: God saith now or never, here is the last way, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> this doth not take, farewell. The end (its plain) is medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>l, that the flesh may be destroyed, and the Spirit may be <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed in the day of Christ: and here let us take notice, though <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ere be severity, yet there is mercy mingled with it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here is Mercy in this, that God will not have such a course <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>en, save when all other helps fail, not till then: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e he will have us to begin with private admonitions, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. Cover the fault as long as may be; if yet no audience then <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ceed unto a second or third, untill such time as the party ceas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to hear the Church; untill that day, this sentence is not to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> inflicted. There is Mercy in this, that God delayeth it so long.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. Here is mercy in this: it is but in <hi>interitum carnis:</hi> it is but for <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> destruction of the flesh, that is the prime end of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n, and then.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. He setteth bounds to the Devil: prescribeth it <hi>Diabolo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>os. Athan,</hi> he sheweth that Satan is limmitted to the flesh, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> shall go no further then the flesh: Again.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. It is not <hi>malum perpetuum, sed ad tempus,:</hi> the end is, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:207123:14"/> the soul may be saved in the day of Christ: (which last w<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> (in the day of Christ) you may apply either to the day of de<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> or the day of Christs appearing:) so that this moderateth<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> severity of the sentence, in this, that it doth not put any into a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> wherein they cannot be saved; we put them rather in a way to saved: <hi>Perirent, nisi perirent,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. Therefore were <hi>Hy<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> delivered to Satan, <hi>that they might learn no<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> blaspheme.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> boasts of his Authority, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.8. that<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Lord gave it him for edification, and not for destruction: So t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the primary intrinsecal end of the Rod of Excommunication is<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the edifying of souls. The wisdom of God hath appointed by sha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> grief, and sorrow of being put out of Christs Family, to humble<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> spirit of him that hath any thing of God, (though secretly) ly<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in him.</p>
            <p>I come now to some Objections to be answered.</p>
            <p>Object. 1. <hi>Is not this a very unlikely way to save souls by put<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> them out of the care of the Church, and out of the fellowship of the p<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of God? and especially to put them into the hands of the Dev<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> may you not more easily reform a wanton within her fathers house, t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> by casting her forth into the stews?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> But <hi>who art thou, O man that disputest against God?</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> will you reason against the wisdom of Christ? You see clearly it his will, that he be put away; and this putting away is the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <hi>livering to Satan:</hi> and the express reason is, <hi>that the flesh may be<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyed, and the soul saved.</hi> A Medicinal depriving of an off<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dor of the comfortable communion of the Saints is a means, a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> mighty through God to humble.</p>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>But what if these persons that we intend to excommunic<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> be found godly: is not this dangerous to carry our selves so to<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> children of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> This hath been spoken to already; but yet some will<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you, that the Apostle speaketh of the <hi>incestuous person,</hi> supposing h<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> godly, that he had not all flesh, but spirit as well as flesh. Yet wave that: I pray you consider to prevent stumbling at Excom<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nication: may not Regenerate persons fall into such grievous sin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>incest</hi> and <hi>murder?</hi> and then why not for a time into contumacy<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Church, which deserveth Excommunication. They that co<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit such sins deserve Excommunication; but the converted n<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> commit such sins, therefore they may deserve to be Excommuni<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, and they that deserve it should have it. Godly men have<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> heard admonition: <hi>Asa</hi> was a good man, yet he was so far fr<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> hearing the Prophet▪ that he claps him up in prison, for being fai<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful; Are we to suspend Excommunication on this supposition, t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> such an one may be seminally, or secretly a child of God? who t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> shall be Excommunicated? It being possible that Grace may<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:207123:14"/> within him: But to shut up this; know that the object of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>xcommunication by Christs appointment, is one that refus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>th to hear the Church, whether he be converted or not.</p>
            <p>Object. 3. <hi>But you will say Excommunication in the Text was for <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ncest, that is a great offence, and you have not such matter against <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ese, that you intend to proceed upon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. The first Answer I shall give you here unto is this. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hough the offence should be in the matter small; yet that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ereth not, but that the Offender should be excommunicated: As <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> said before, so say I still; and it will be found a truth for ever: <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>he Reason of Excommunication is not for the first ossence only; <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ut for contumacy and impenitency joyned with it: so that look <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>; Unbelief is in some sence the only condemning sin; that is thus, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hatever sins a man hath committed; if he did but believe, he were <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ife: so whatever offence a man hath committed, if he would <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ear the first admonition, or the second, or the Churches admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>on, he should not be proceeded on, he may not be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ted. As Unbelief is the sin that damneth, so neglecting to hear <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e Church is the sin that excommunicateth. If a Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r was guilty of the higest crime imaginable. Suppose it <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y, &amp;c.</hi> Yet if he giveth evidence of Repentance, he is not to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> cast out: and yet if the offence be never so small, if he hears <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ot the Church: and therein Christ; he is to proceeded against. No <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>oner did this incestuous person discover sorrows for his sin, but <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e Apostle is as urgent for his absolution, as before his Excomu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>cation. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2 6, 7. sufficient to such a man is this punishment <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hich was inflicted of many: so that contrarwise ye ought rather <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> forgive him, and comfort him, lest perhaps, <hi>such an one should <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> swallowed up with over-much sorrow:</hi> And you shall find that <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e Brethren for the Presbyterian Government are of this mind: <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ear their great Champion, Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> in his Divine right of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hurch-government. <hi>p.</hi> 226. A Fault may be light, and small in <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s rise. (mark it light and small) so long as it is private which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rveth not Excommuaication: but if contumacy shall come to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e fault, (that is, if the party shall neglect private and publique <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>dmonition) as it is here in its growth, and tendency to scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ze many, it is not small. Will ye hear one much unbiassed, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>er himself. Si aliquis Ecclesiae Minister, &amp;c. Tom.</hi> 2. in <hi>Gen.</hi> 21. If <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> be any Officer of the Church should not absolve me, but drive <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e off from the holy Communion, though the matter of offence <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ere but light, yee I believe I should despair with <hi>Iudas,</hi> and go and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ang my self.</p>
            <p>And we find also, that whoever was three days together from <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hurch without urgent necessity, was to be excommunicated, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ording to the fixth general Council in <hi>Trull.</hi> In Constantinople
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:207123:15"/> can 80. Do not some think it a small matter to be three or<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> times absent from the Church-meetings without any cause? But 2. I answer that all things being considered, the fa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of both these delinquent-members will (for ought I<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> see, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>2</label> yet to the contrary) weigh in the scal with the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the incestuous person. For though this sin of the <hi>Corinthia<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> called an unheard of sin, <hi>not named among the Gentiles;</hi> yet sure<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is a kind of Hyperbolick expression <hi>not heard,</hi> that is, not very c<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon among the Gentiles, but detested by some of them. There instances among the Prophane Authors of this sin. <hi>Antiochus</hi> the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Demetrius</hi> by his fathers consent matched with his mother<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Law as <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in the life of <hi>Demetrius</hi> doth observe. So <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> married his father <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his wife. There was incest.</p>
            <p>The meaning then is, that this sin was abominable to som<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the civil heathens: and so we may say of the delinquencies wh<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> both these are charged with. I shall speak here a little plainly.</p>
            <p>For the one of them. Mistriss <hi>S.E.</hi> she is accused among o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> things for lying more then three times: sufficiently proved.<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> us look a little into this sin, and perhaps we may say of it, i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> not named among the Gentiles: sure it was a sin abominated<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the heathen. It is said of <hi>Epaminondas</hi> that he abhorred <hi>mendacium<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cosum,</hi> a jesting lie, though he was an Heathen; So that the Apo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> aggravation will fall on this sin also. It is a fault that is not na<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> among the heathen: that is, it is detestable to some of the heath<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> so <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Paraeus</hi> open the words. And the <hi>Persian:</hi> &amp; <hi>Indians</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a Law, that whoever had heen thrice convicted of lying, should<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> on pain of death never s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eak a word more all his life after.</p>
            <p>I beseech you my Brethren, let us not account of sins only<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cording to the esteem of Nations: let us look into the boo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> God; and see whethet lying be a small sin First God saith<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>presly, that there is no sin more against godliness, then lying<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 63.8. <hi>Surely they are my People:</hi> How prove you that? I have<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> evidence of it; <hi>They are Children that will not lie.</hi> So that ly<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> seemeth to be inconsistent with the relation of Children: thi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> such a spot as is not in Gods own Children: nay God engag<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> himself? if you look narrowly to that Scripture) for his peo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>these a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the People that will not lie.</hi> Secondly it is one of the se<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> things that God abominateth. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.16, 17, 18, 19, <hi>These<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> things doth the Lord hate, yea seven are an abomination unto him:<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> proud look, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood, An he<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that deviseth wicked immaginations, feet that be swift in running<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> mischief, a false witness that speaketh lies, and him that soweth<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cord among Brethren, &amp;c.</hi> Among these seven things abominated<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> God, lying is twice repeated: and therefore it is no slight thi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> it seemeth to be most abominable. And what though, so<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:207123:15"/> amongst us, should account this a l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttle sin: so was <hi>Sodomy</hi> one <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ty by the Inhabitants of <hi>Sodom.</hi> Thirdly, though men will rank <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s sin among the lower-form sins, yet it may further appear that <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>od doth not, in that dreadful word, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. <hi>But the fearful <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d unbelieving, and the abominable, and Murderers, and Whoremongers, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d Sorcerers, and Idolaters, and all liars shall have their part in the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ke, which burneth with brimstone: which is the second death.</hi> Mark it, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ith what sinners are liar, coupled? you couple them with sinners, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ilty only of vain thoughts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the Scripture coupleth them <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ith Unbelievers, and abominable, with Whoremongers, Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s, and Idolatets: view the place again: it is not said all the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>il, all the murderers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but all liars, and what shall become of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>em? they must all to the lake; and may not we turn them out of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e Church of God, whom God will turn down to Hell? Fourthly, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> is safer in some sence to tolerate an <hi>incestuous person,</hi> then a liar <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> a Church: especially such an one as soweth discord, a disconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed liar, as this woman was. The peace of the Church is not so <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ndangered by an unclean wretch, as by a liar, there can be no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>union with such. It is (as one saith) the breaking of all Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y: there can be no converse between man and man where this is. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nd what mischief this lying woman hath been likely to do amongst <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s, you are not altogether ignorant.</p>
            <p>But to come to the other woman: she hath bin accused for neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ecting fellowship with the people of God, and in that for Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ant-breaking; but chiefly hath been dealt with, for that scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>alous carriage of hers in running away from her husband. Though <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ome may make this a light sin to, yet this is a sin against the light of Nature: and so cometh under the Character the Apostle <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>iveth. The Heathen could have taught her otherwise: the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ight of Nature led them to <hi>co-habitation ubi tu Cajus, ibi ego Caja:</hi> was a solemn usage in their marriages; and therefore we may be <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ble to give account to others, that this is no slight offence, for the Heathen knew by the light of Nature, that as they were to be one <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>lesh: so they were to live together. The Scripture saith, <hi>Let the wife see that she fears her husband,</hi> Eph. 5.33. But to run from an husband, argueth a base esteem of the husband, and to take such <hi>a vile woman</hi> for her companion, that had run before — some of you know how, greatneth her sin, and maketh it the more scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous. <hi>Hagar</hi> was culpable in running from her Mistress: but a wife much more, in running from her husband.</p>
            <p>The Apostle saith of wives, that they must <hi>be keepers at home, and obedient to their husbands, that the word of God may not be blasphemed, Tit.</hi> 2.5. How much the Name of God suffered (you know in part) by her leaving her husband: I am sure I have been hit in the teeth with the scandalousness of the fact: the streets of the City have
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:207123:16"/> rung with the disobedience of that wretch, Mistris <hi>M. A.</hi> by na<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> I approve of Dr. <hi>Taylors</hi> Exposition on the last named Scripture,<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thing here condemned (saith he) is the affection of gadding at a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> or all hours with disposition of hearing, or telling news, or affe<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing merriment and expensive company, accounting the house a p<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son. But surely it doth with a witness reprove flying from ho<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> flying as she did from her home; if they may not gad from ho<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> they may not fly from home. By this she hath stained her self,<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> profession, her husband, wronged him exceedingly, as if he w<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> such a <hi>Nabal</hi> that none could dwell with him, and therein very m<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> belyeth him. Besides in it she throws up the trust, that God<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> put into her hands, of sharing in the government of houshold affa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in it she neglected her children, gave an ill president to them t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> were grown up to be capable of infection by so ill example. So t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> you see the offences of both these, are in this like the <hi>incestuous p<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sons</hi> sin, they are such, as are not named among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> indeed abominable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> 3. But then thirdly, let us consider the sins of these<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> men, with some circumstances going before and after.</p>
            <p>First, For Mistris <hi>S. E.</hi> I shall give you a little account of h<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and it must be this account: that she was burdensome to many<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> us before she came under Church-admonition; shee took liberty<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> speaking in the Church for sometime, and being reproved by me f<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> it, from that time there was a visible decay of affection to me; have much observed, that when I often treated with her, I fou<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> her of a troublesome disconten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed spirt, quarrelling either with t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Church in general, or with several members, whom she would i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peach, and being told by me it was an irregularity, and admoni<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed to discharge her duties to them, she <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as offended at me, yet p<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sisted notwithstanding: And I am confident that there is scarce o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Brother, or Sister, that can bear witness of her faithfulness in<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proving privately; though she so much blazoned abroad, suppos<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> or real infirmities, and I leave it to you to judge whether this w<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> not schismatical.</p>
            <p>She was also observed to dislike those persons, as unfit for Churc<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> fellowship, whom the Church approved, and was a great stick<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> against the Church, for several persons, whom they could not co<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fortably close with, yea she would seldom discover her likeing<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> disliking of persons proposed, till the Church had given their de<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sive sentence. Thus from time to time she was a Bryar in our side But then when private Admonition was given her by a Brother<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> two, which was done several times; this we can say that there w<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> hardly any one that came from her, but with a sad heart (so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> was her carriage, and so lofty, and her spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amed.) But wh<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> she was under Church-admonition concerning several things; s<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:207123:16"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>as found tripping very much in reference to her tongue, and lying <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>regiously: so that the whole Church could bear witness against <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r; And being farther pressed to hear the Church, she refused, and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>f my memory fail not) she said, she would be drawn asunder by <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ild horses rather then come amongst us. And though she had lif— <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> up her right hand to heaven, to walk in fellowship with us, yet <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>th she separated from us, and to this day sought not reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>on, neither hath she expressed Repentance for her sins: but she <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>th justified her self in all that she hath done; instead of confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>g her lies, she stands in her justification; and though she accus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Church in general, and particular members thereof falsely, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e performeth no duty, that according to <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15. she is bound <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, of telling it between him and thee, in order to the making any <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> us sensible of a (supposed) sin.</p>
            <p>For Mistriss <hi>M. A.</hi> Her coming amongst us is somewhat observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e; Before such time, as we were a Church, we had a meeting of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hristians, wherein none were admitted, but those that gave an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>unt of the grounds of their hope; at length Mistris <hi>A.</hi> proposed <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>er self to this Society, and spake very confidently of her conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>: on a sudden she was (as some observed) stopt in her speech; <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ving a little before spoken much of her assurance, yet discovered <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> much ignorance, that I believe not one person was satisfied with <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>at, which she spake as her experience; therefore she was denied. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ut a considerable time after the Church was constituted, she defir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Church-fellowship; And then came in with so much difficulty, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>at (as I am credibly informed, for I was then absent.) Mr. <hi>Stone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> the then Teacher of this Church, hinted to her to this purpose, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>at the Church had stretched to the utmost line of Charity in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>er to her Reception; and therefore advised her that her future de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eanour might be such, as might give better satisfaction concerning <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>er for the future, then they had for the present. Since when, though <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e did engage to fellowship with us: I think this I may say, there <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> not a Brother, or Sister here, that can bear witness of her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rming any Church-duty to them, of admonition, exhortation, or <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eproof; and if any of you can witness for her in these things, I <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>arge you to discover it; I speak this, because if she hereafter <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ting dirt in this, or that, or the other persons face by Reports, you <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ay look on such things as slanders, or on her as a Covenant-brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>er in not observing the Rule of Christ. A considerable time after <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>is there happened to be some heats, heats did I say? yea a flame <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>as kindled in her spirit, against a sister in law of hers, who is in <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ommunion with us. The business grew to that height, that the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>lders were necessitated to examine it: At that time I came enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed to her as the party innocent, rather then the other; but when <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs were examined, I found she had wronged her sister exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:207123:17"/> by defaming her in the <hi>Eastern</hi> parts amongst her Relat<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> as well as among several members here, and never discharged<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> duty towards her. She carried her self so dis-ingeniously, that I<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> hardly charity for her at that time to judge her gracious; Fo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> would endure no council, no admonition, though tendered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> bowels: And though her sister was many waies the wronged<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> son, and begged her with tears not to go off in a passion, yet o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> went in a disdaining way. After long pressing her to confess wronging of her sister: at length, it seemed, she did go to he<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> some outside way, she did somewhat that looked like Repenta<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> or that we would feign one as a retraction. But it seemeth<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that day she had rankour in her spirit against me; for she hath<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fest since; that the reason why she would not speak with me, th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> desired by me, was, because I was unfaithful in that business:<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> if I were unfaithful in that business, ever let me be so unfait<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> if I were unfaithful, it was in not reproving her more cuttingly<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> words were too soft I fear. However she patcheth up a peace<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> her sister, apd skinneth over the wound; But within a little after, she carrieth her self frowardly, not only to her Sister, b<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> all the Brethren that had discourse with her about her miscarria<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and particularly about her neglecting Church-fellowship (w<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> was too apparent) and her discontent grew to that height, tha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> grew angry with her own husband, and in her passion ran from<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which being so scandalous, the Church thought themselves obl<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to admonish her of that, and other sins, but she breaketh forth passionate speeches, defaming the Church, and despising their<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> refusing from that day to this to hear the Church, and perswa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> her husband to an undue, and unjust separation from us. She is contented to be a Covenant-breaker her self, but would have ot<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> break the Oath of God under which they lie.</p>
            <p>Give me leave yet further to aggravate the sin of both these<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties in a comparison with the <hi>incestuous person:</hi> First, in all li<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hood the <hi>incestuous person</hi> had never been reproved for this si<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> his, as may be infer'd from <hi>ver.</hi> 2. They did not <hi>mourn over him;</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> so have these; these have been admonished privately, and<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> likely.</p>
            <p>Secondly, When the <hi>incestuous person</hi> was put away, the next<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> we hear of him is his Repentance, but these, since their suspen<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> which is a kind of Excommunication, yet have shewed no Re<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mation; instead of sorrowing they rejoyce, and think themse<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> worthy to be cried up, and to sit in the highest places of the S<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gogue, for their stout carriage towards a poor Church of Chris<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, We do not find that the <hi>incestuous person</hi> jeared at<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Sentence of excommunication, but so do these: Here I cannot<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> take notice of one thing; after such time as <hi>Gannicle</hi> was thr<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:207123:17"/>
               <hi>to utter destruction: therefore thy life shall go for his life, and thy people for his people?</hi> How many appointed by God to the sword of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication are there, yet let alone every where? Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> in his <hi>Divine Right of Church-government, pag.</hi> 520, saith, that they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e co-partners with the wicked, who dispence the bread to them who are knowingly dead in sins. Wo to them that say they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusted with the keyes of Heaven, and yet open the door wide to them whom God would have to be kept from his holy Hill; and do not exclude them from communion, whom God would have to be put away from the midst of them: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat can men say, why they do not difference the precious from the vile out of the Pulpit, as well as in the Pulpit? they are affraid to offer in the Pulpit mercy to the wicked and impenitent; but why do they give the Seals of mercy and forgiveness to them, that are walking openly in the way to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction? It is a terrible word, that in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.19. <hi>And will ye po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute me among my people for handfuls of Barley, and for pieces of bread, to slay the souls that should not die, and to save the souls alive that should not live, by your lying to my people that hear your lies?</hi> To save them that should die how sad is this? How then dare men say, this is the blood of the Covenant shed for the Remission of your sins? Drink ye all of it? How can men say this to a company of loose persons, and disorderly walkers? How can the mother be guiltless of the death of her child, that giveth him poison with this caution, that she telleth him it is poison: so do many Ministers; they tell men of the danger of unworthy Receiving; crying, take heed you come not to the table of the Lord, it is pioson; and yet give the Bread to them. Men fondly relieve themselves with a charge they give their people, that they come not unpreparedly to the Lords ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: But alas!— they plead for more then a Doctrinal power that they have to bar the wicked from holy things by Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and yet improve it not.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But it is pleaded, that they suspend from the Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I think they are hardly agreed on that point to this day, whether there be such a censure as suspension appointed by Christ, and many of them confess that they use suspension as a prudential, to comply with their Brethren, rather then as an Instituted Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. But truly this is to be for a lamentation, that such an indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable Ordinance, as Excommunication should be laid aside, and a Prudential shall serve turn. How doth this Intrench on Christs wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in appointing this Rod in his house, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen it shall not be used from one year to another, though the miscarriages of many calls for it: Sad is it that prudential Remedies shall excommunicate the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of Excommunication: this is to be matter of lamentation.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But they would say, they would Excommunicate, but they want the Magistrates power.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:207123:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I shall give in the Answers of two men of Renown to this. First, Mr. <hi>Rutherford,</hi> he saith, who gave the keyes of the Kingdom of Heaven to the Magistrates? It is confest, if there were no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Magistrates, the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rch might Excommunicate; and shall the Magistrate, because he is a Christian, spoil the Church of the power she had; when she wanted a Magistrate?</p>
            <p>But then hear Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his <hi>Gildas Salvianus,</hi> or Reformed Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor. I shall give you his words. <hi>pag.</hi> 214. <hi>How many Ministers in</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland <hi>be there that know not their own charge! that never cast out one obstinate sinner! no nor brought one to publick confession, and expression of repenta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce, and promise of Reformation? No nor admonished one publikely to call him to such Repentance?</hi> May not we lament it in <hi>Exon?</hi> The great out-cryers against Separation (say I) pretend that all within the compass of their Parishes are Church-members. And yet for many years together they neglect Church-censures, saith Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> hear him again, <hi>pag.</hi> 222. <hi>We are sent, as Christs Embas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadours to speak in his Name, and not in the Princes, and by his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we do our work, as from him we have our Commission. The same power that you have to preach without or against the Magistrates com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, the same have you to exercise Pastoral Guidance and Discipline without it,</hi> &amp;c. And again, <hi>pag.</hi> 226. <hi>The Magistrate fineth and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soneth: that is his part: It is your part to bring them to open Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; or to cast them out: Doth not the Magistracy of</hi> England <hi>punish ten, twenty, what if I say an hundred Swearers, Drunkards, or Sabbath-breakers by the sword, for one that the Elders of the Church do punish by censures, or bring to publick repentance for the satisfaction of the Church.</hi> And again, <hi>pag.</hi> 227. <hi>What had the Church of Christ done till the daies of</hi> Constantine <hi>the great: if it had no better Pastors then you, that will not govern it without the joint compulsion of the Magistrate? Discipline, and severe Discipline was exercised for three hundred years together, where the Prince did not give them so much as a Protection, nor Toleration, but persecuted them to the death.</hi> And again, <hi>pag.</hi> 228, <hi>Are the keyes of Christs Kingdom so useless that they will not open, and shut without the help of the sword? If they have contracted any rust, by which they are made less fit for service, next to the Prelates, we may thank our selves, that let them lie so long unused.</hi> In <hi>pag.</hi> 232. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> raiseth an Objection, that we are but single Pastors, and therefore cannot excommunicate men alone, he answereth to this largely, and amongst other things, thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have you none in your Parish, not one or two to make ruling Elders of, that by their conjunction you may be authorized to do more then now you do? I mean according to your own principles. And what hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth but you may join together if you will? If it must needs be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Pastors conjunct, that must exercise any act of Discipline, why is it so don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? Doth any forbid them? It is a reproachful charge upon all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:207123:18"/> the Ministers in the Country, to say, that Discipline is cast aside, becaus they can get none to join with them in the execution. Remember this day and remember often the danger that cometh to Ministers, and people w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere the leaven is not cast out.</hi> And let this be for a lamentation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋse</hi> 2. The second Use is of caution seve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al ways.</p>
            <p>First, Caution to them that yet have not joined themselves to any particular Church, let them beware how they joine themselves to any Church, where Discipline is neglected. The leaven of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness, is leaven to this day. There is as great danger in wicked com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany now, as ever there was: if so be, you may join with visibly unleavened Societies, beware how ye joine with others, lest after you thank your selves for all the polution and misery you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, by joining your selves to undisciplined Congregations.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let it be a caution to you my Brethren, and to others, not to be offended at a Church, in case some prove rotten and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sound. The Apostle tels us, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. <hi>There must be Heresies among you, that they which are approved, may be made manifest among you.</hi> If there were none, what would become of the Rod? The rod is made for the back of Offenders. Be not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at <hi>Corinth,</hi> though there be found an incestuous person there: nor at us, though a Liar and Covenant-breaker be amongst us: they are to be cast out. Be offended at us rather, when we neglect Church-Discipline.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋse</hi> 3. The third Use is of information. This informeth us, what a wise God we have to deal with, who can make the most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely means serviceable to his ends; who can make Satan do his own work. That is to be considered to day. A man would think that such a censure should totally and finally harden a sinner. It would so, if God did not otherwise dispose of it, if it were not Christs institution. Oh, How is carnal reason here <hi>non-plust!</hi> My own reason tels me, that this days meeting (not considering it as an institution) will harden these wretches more: But when I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member an institution of Christ, when I remember that God would have the Church convened, and that to <hi>deliver to Satan for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of the flesh:</hi> It giveth me some hopes, when I remember that God did make the earth to help the woman, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.16. Why may he not here make the Serpent the Devil, to help the woman This is admirable, that the flesh must be destroyed, and Satan must haue an hand in it: What strange tools can God work with?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋse</hi> 4. The fourth and the last se is of Exhortation to the Church of God to four things.</p>
            <p>First, Boast not over the fallen. It is by Grace that thou stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est. If God let thee alone before the setting of the Sun, thou wilt turn thy back as much on Christ and his people, as these have done; thou wilt contemn Christs institutions if let alone, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:207123:19"/> private and publique Admonition, as much as these: thou wilt dispise the Church in thy heart and tongue, as much as these. When the Gentiles were in the olive tree, in the Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. And the Jew cut off. The Apostle was jealous that this priviledge would swell the Gentiles into great thoughts of themselves, and into a contempt of the Jews: and therefore he cautioneth them, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>Boast not against the Branches,</hi> that is, against the Branches that are broken off. If God let thee alone, thou wilt be the fourth person that will be thrown out of this house of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Boast not of thy self too much. Perhaps thou vauntest that thou hast kept thy self within compass; But art not thou guilty of such wickedness. That had the Brethren been faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to thy soul, thou mighest also have come under censure this day: or perhaps thou delighest in contemplative wickedness, and art but a painted wall, a guilded post, a very Formalist, full of envy pride, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Know this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Satan will be contented to have the inward Rooms, if he cannot possess the whole house. Thou art as safely the Devils by indulging to a secret sin, as if thou wert guilty of an open scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous evil: nay in some sense in a far worse condition; for if thy wickedness did break forth, thou mighest enjoy this sharp privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Excommunication, (whose end is for the destruction of the <hi>flesh, that the Spirit might be saved in the day of the Lord,</hi>) which now, because thy sin is secret, thou canst not enjoy. It is true, the Excommunicates are put under the power of Satan judicially, but thou art under his Power already, thou maist fear, thou art delivered to Satan mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ally, to be hardened: but these are to be delivered, though judicially; yet medicinally also to be humbled, shamed and softned, <hi>that the Spirit may be saved.</hi> Again.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thou that boastest, that thou carriest things cleverly, know that there is a doctrinal Excommunication, that many Church-members may be under, many more then we can possibly beware of. When your Ministers declare from Gods word, that <hi>Hypocrites shall not inherit heaven, &amp;c.</hi> That Word of God hath Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity enough to bind you over to the day of Christ, unless you repent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this, that God may detect you before you die, and likely he will, and therefore boast not of your secresie in sinning, your paint may fall off: the stake in the hedge, though at the first it looketh green, yet after a while, it will wither, and shew it self to be but a stake, and not a living Branch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cùn</hi> was at first a Sacrificer, and yet at length cast out, cast out of the sight of the Lord, out of his fathers family, from the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God will not always s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffer you to abuse his own patience and the good opinion of Beholders, and the place of your standin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:207123:19"/> in the Church of God. A dead oak may be left alone in a wood, but a dead vine may not be let alone in a Vineyard.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Through this cloud, Labor what ye can to shine the brighter, let me bespeak you in the words of the Apostle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.14, 15, 16. <hi>Do all things without murmerings and disputings, that ye may be blameless and harmless; the Sons of God without rebuke in the midst of a crooked and perverse Nation, among whom ye shine as Lights in the world, holding forth the word of life, that I may rejoice in the day of Christ, that I have not run in vain, nor labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in vain.</hi> I beseech you repair Gods honour and the Churches what you may, by shining the brigher, and amongst other ways this is one, let it be in those Graces that are most opposite to the sins of the Excommunicates, to those sins you are come, to witness against this day: You have thrown out one already for his Heretical Principles, and not hearing the Church; Do you covet the more to be sound in the Faith, and to be stedfast and unmoveable in a form of wholsome words: And for this end, I cannot but commend your purpose of subscribing a profession of faith this day. So for these that are to be thrown out this day, the more lying one hath been guilty of; the more do you speak truth one to another,; and let there not be a lying tongue in the midst of us: and the more another is found disobedient, I beseech you labour the more to keep your bounds at home, as also in this Church of Christ; and here also I cannot but approve of your purpose to subscribe a Covenant that will be a fence against a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Spirit.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Let me beseech you to love Heaven the better for this day, and the sad occasion of it. Here we see, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing all our Covenants and Engagements; yet we are a mixed people: the Leaven is amongst us to this day. Let us take a view of Heaven, when putting some on the borders of hell, In Heaven there are no mixtures, there are none Leavened, there are none that cause division; there they are all of one heart, and of one peice. Let this provoke us to long for Heaven: Here is lying and deceitfulness, fickleness and levity: but in Heaven there is no such inconstant and scandalous company: there are all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full friends, a faithfull Father, a faithfull Christ, a faithfull Spirit, faithfull Angels, all faithfull friends. Here ever and anon we have the Briar and the Thorn (such the earth brought forth ever since the fall) here the <hi>Canaanite</hi> and the <hi>Perizite</hi> are amongst us; but in Heaven no Briar groweth. let us be invited to love hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the better.</p>
            <p>The Church is compared to the Kingdom of Heaven, and it should be so here, into which no unclean thing should enter; but yet it is not so in this lower Heaven, in this house of God,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:207123:20"/> Here are vessels of dishonour that appear so, and here vessels get rust, and the very appointing excommunication speaketh what God saw his Church would need. But Excommunication is no more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Heaven above, since the Angelss were thence cast out.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the Sermon which was delivered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Persons were Excommunicated.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="justification_for_excommunication">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:207123:20"/>
            <head>After the persons were Excommunicated: there were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven these following Reasons, why a Church of Christ should then renew their Covenant with God, why any of the members thereof are justly Excommunicated.</head>
            <div n="1" type="reason">
               <head>
                  <hi>Reason</hi> 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He excommunicating of obstinate, and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent members, is the purging out of filth, which was got within such a Church: this is implied in that excommunication is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. under the Metaphor of purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Purge out therefore the old leaven;</hi> and if we peruse the Records of Scripture, we shall find, that whensoever any filth was <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t into the house of God, by sinful remisness in the people of God, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ey did not satisfie themselves with throwing out the filth, but so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>mnly renewed their Covenant. Thus they did in <hi>Asa</hi>'s time: a <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ophet cometh, and telleth <hi>Asa</hi> that how they <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ere defiled, when <hi>Asa</hi> heard those words,<note place="margin">Hebr. Abominations.</note>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> took courage and put away the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e idols out of the Land, but what? was that all? No, And <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y entred into a covenant, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.8. and <hi>vers.</hi> 12. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>red: they did both put away the Abominations that were <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ong them, and they did bind themselves more firmly to all <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ties of piety towards God, comprized under the phrase of seeking <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Lord; so in <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> days, he commanded <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Levites</hi> to carry forth the filthiness out of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> holy place, but that is not all,<note n="*" place="margin">Ʋnder this word filthiness is compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, what ever was brought into the Temple to pollute the true worship of God. <hi>Larg. Anot. in loc.</hi>
                  </note> he would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ave them enter into Covenant with God <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>in, as appears by comparing the fifth &amp; the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>th <hi>ver.</hi> of the 29. chapt. of the second book <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>hron.</hi> Thus in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time, after they <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> been mixt with strangers: the seed of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>el,</hi> such as were truly <hi>Israelites,</hi> that did
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:207123:21"/> not disgrace <hi>Israel,</hi> from whom they descended, they put away all strangers, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.2. and also renewed<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. Fidelity or sureness, or a sure thing to note, (<hi>saith</hi> Mr. <hi>Caril</hi>) that a well grounded Covenant is a sure, and firm, and irrevokable act.</note> their Covenant <hi>ver.</hi> 38. Because of all this we make a sure Covenant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reason">
               <head>
                  <hi>Reason.</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>a</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, quia eliguntur persone inter quas &amp; res ac conditiones propter quas, foedus initur <hi>Buxtorf.</hi>
                  </note>Such purging out of filth qualifieth such a Church for renewing their covenant with God, the Hebrew word, <hi>Berith</hi> (a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant) cometh from <hi>Barah,</hi> which signifieth to choose exactly, and judiciously, only choice per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons are fit for Covenanting-work; the Lord promiseth that he will cause his people to pass under the Rod, and so he would bring them into the bond of the Covenant,<note place="margin">Totum populum Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelis ita probabo, &amp; recognoscam, ut Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor gregem ad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiendos in foedus &amp; caulam meam bonas: improbos{que} abdicandos. <hi>Jun. in loc. Thus</hi> Polanus <hi>also, and the large Anotat. expounds this placc.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.37. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> expoundeth the words thus: as if God had said, I will prove and try the whole people o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Israel</hi> as a Shepherd doth his flock: that I may take the good, and sound into the fold of my Covenant, and cast out the wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sound; this interpretation is not only favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but fully approved, (saith, Mr. <hi>Caril</hi>) in the words immediatly following <hi>vers.</hi> 38. <hi>I will bring you into the bond of the Covenant, and I will purge out from among you the rebels, and them that transgress against me;</hi> this was the choice qualification of those that renewed thei<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Covenant, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 10.28. They had not only knowledge and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, but they had separated themselves from the people of the lands, unto the law of God: they had purged out filth from<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Among them. Such a Church before the Rebels are purged out from among them, is not so qualified for covenanting with the Lord<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reason">
               <head>
                  <hi>Reason</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>It is no small affliction to such a Church, that there is need of the dreadfull Censure of Excommunication to be inflicted on any of its members; it cannot but be a time of trouble to the whole Church, when any of its members are cut off by Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: it cannot but be as great a trouble as it is to our natural bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, when a finger, or a toe, or an arm, or a leg are cut of<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:207123:21"/> Such time therefore is seasonable for such work. I will cause you saith the Lord, to pass under the Rod, and so I will bring you in. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the bond of the Covenont, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.37.</p>
               <p>This was one cause of that Covenant in <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiahs</hi> dayes. We are in great distress, <hi>Neh.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pios sub virgam transmittit Deus, ut ad foederis exhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem eos inducat quum nolit eos sui juris esse, &amp; pro arbitrio carnis vivere. <hi>Polon. in loc.</hi>
                  </note> 9.37. And because of all this we make a sure Covenant, <hi>vers.</hi> 38.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="reason">
               <head>
                  <hi>Reason.</hi> 4.</head>
               <p>Excommunication of Incorrigible members ought to be joined with fasting, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. the Apostle blameth the Corinthian Church, because they had not mourned,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> refers to the stile of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and denotes the solemnity usuall among the <hi>Jews,</hi> of putting on mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing habits, and wail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over them that were Excommunicated. <hi>Leigh. in loc.</hi> When there was Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they did antiently fast. <hi>Trap. in loc.</hi>
                  </note> that he that had done that deed, might be taken away from among them; and the proper busines, of a fasting day, is entring into, or renewing Covenant with God: the Covenant in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time, came in the close of a fasting day, as appears, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.1, 38. compared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="reason">
               <head>
                  <hi>Reason</hi> 5.</head>
               <p>At such a time Sathan hath faster hold of some, that were of such a Church: and therefore at such a time God should have faster hold of such a Church. Such as are Excommunicated, they are (as hath been told you) delivered to Sathan, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5.<note n="*" place="margin">Hoc illud est, quod Christus dicit, fieri sicut ethnicum, sive publicanum, <hi>Matth. 18.17. Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in loc.</hi> So <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za, Calvin, Paraeus, Alapide, Estius, Morton, Leigh.</hi> large Annot. and the Dutch Annot. inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret this place.</note> And therefore such a Church should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver up themselves A fresh to God; such poor wretches are given up to Judicial hardness, so that they are sorry for nothing so much, but that they with such a Church entred into Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God; they have rerracted and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canted what formerly they did: and therefore such a Church to manifest that they are still of the same mind, and that they do not repent of what they have done, should renew their Covenant. Such wretches they have renewed their Covenant with Hell, and Sathan, and therefore such a Church should renew their Covenant with God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="reason">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:207123:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Reason</hi> 6..</head>
               <p>At such a time such a Church seeth sad instances of its prone<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to backslide from God, and what they should do, if God should leav<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> them to themselves: and a Covenant is a Golden Girdle to tie<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> fast to God; it is a joyning our selves to th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.5.<note n="*" place="margin">Let us glue our selves to the Lord; so some: let us bind our selves to the Lord, not only as the borrower doth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to the usurer for a time; but as the wife doth her self to her husband, for ever, saith Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gess</hi> in his Sermon before the Parliam. on those words.</note> Seeing therefore such<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Church seeth at such a time in a more espec<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all manner their pronness to suffer this Golde<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Girdle to loosen, and untie, to dis-join ond un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glue themselves from God: therefore it is ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry seasonable for such a Church at such a tim<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to enter into bond again unto the Lord, to ti<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> this Golden Girdle yet faster: to glue them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selves once more to the Lord, that so God an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and they may never part. One main end o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Covenanting is to prevent starting aside fro<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> God. For this end blessed <hi>Hooper</hi> was willin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to be tied to the stake, because he was flesh a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> well as spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="reason">
               <head>
                  <hi>Reason.</hi> 7.</head>
               <p>At such a time Satan will be tempting and assaulting others i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> such a Church: when Satan and the world have got any to Aposta<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tize, and to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art from God and his ways; they are encouraged t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> set upon more, to endeavour the seducing of more of the Member<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of such a Church: Now there is no such way to prevent Satans d<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sign, as for such a Church to renew their Covenant; therefore wa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Israel</hi> to renew their Covenant, le<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> there should be among them any, who<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> heart turneth away from the Lord<note n="*" place="margin">Or as the Greek and Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die explain it, that there be not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ayns. in loc.</note>
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10, 12, 18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="reason">
               <head>
                  <hi>Reason</hi> 8.</head>
               <p>It is a very choice Mercy to have filth purged out of Church of Christ, though by excommunicating some of its me<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers, in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.38. 'Its promised as no small mercy that God wou<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> purge out from among his people the Rebel<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and such as thransgress against God.<note place="margin">The Doctrine that <hi>Dr.</hi> Burges in the first Par. Sermon, raiseth from <hi>Jer. 50.5.</hi> is this, when God vouchsafe<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> any deliverance to his Church, especially from Babilon, then it is m<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> seasonable and necessary to close with God by a more solemn, strict a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> inviolable Covenant, to be his, and only his for ever. See it largely pros<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hrough the Sermon.</note> Th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:207123:22"/> might further appear by the motives, whereby the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>resseth the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> to excommunicate the incestuous <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>thian,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5, 6.7. now this is the use that Gods People should <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ake of any choice mercy, thereby to engage themselves more close<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y to God; this is the motive that <hi>Moses</hi> urgeth to perswade the <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>aelites</hi> to enter into a special Covenant with God, beside the solemn Covenant which he made with them (and they with him) in <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>eb, Deut.</hi> 29.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.9, 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="reason">
               <head>
                  <hi>Reason</hi> 9.</head>
               <p>At such a time, such a Church stands in more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y need of Gods renewing his Covenant with them, to have God <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aster bound unto them: And then God is in a special manner, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>illing thereunto, see this most evidently demonstrated in <hi>Jer.</hi> 32. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rom <hi>v.</hi> 37. to the 42. <hi>v.</hi> &amp; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17, 18. it is but reasonable therefore <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hat such a Church should then be willing to renew their Covenant <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ith God, and thereby bind themselves faster unto his Majesty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="reason">
               <head>
                  <hi>Reason</hi> 10.</head>
               <p>This is the likliest means to enable and incline such a Church, to purge out what filth may remain in the midst of them, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd to keep more filth from getting within such a Church for the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>uture. God hath promised that he will pruge out from such a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>le as renew their Covenant with him all the Rebels, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.38. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd he hath promised to establish such a Church for a People to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>imself. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.12, 13, besides hereby such a Church, such a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>le are more engaged to purge out all the remaining leaven, and to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eep out the uncircumcised, and the Philistine from entering with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n the gates of Zion, and so are likly to become, and to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>erved a new lump, as they are unleavened: it is very warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table therefore for us this day, to take up their their words in <hi>Nehe.</hi> 9.38.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:207123:23"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="covenant">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:207123:23"/>
            <head>Because of all this, we make a sure Covenant, and write it.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Believe that there is one only God in three Persons, the Father, the Son and the Holy Ghost; Infinite in Being, Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Goodness and Power: The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, Preserver and Disposer of all things, and the most just and mercifull Lord of All.</p>
            <p>I Belive that Mankind, being fallen by his sin from God and Happiness, under the wrath of God, the curse of his Law, and the power of the Devil: God so loved the world that he gave his only Son to be their Redeemer, who being God, and one with the Father, did take to him our Nature, and became man, being conceived of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost in the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and born of her, and named JESUS CHRIST: and having lived on Earth without sin, and wrought many Miracles: for a witness of his Truth he gave up himself a Sacrifie for our sins, and a Ransom for us, in suffering death upon the Cross, &amp; being buried, he rose again the third day, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ascended into Heaven, where he is Lord of All, in Glory with the Father: and having ordained, that All that truly repent and believe in him, and love him above <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ll things, and sincerely obey him, and that to the death
<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>